Today, I sat down with Bernardo Bilotta, founder of Stables Money.
Stables allows users globally to save and spend money in Stablecoins
with a focus on Asia-Pacific regions.
Bernardo started Stables in early 2021,
back when the total supply of Stablecoins was only about $50 billion,
a mere 20% of today's $250 billion total supply.
He and the team built and launched the application
with the goal of offering a dollar savings account
to those who may be seeking alternatives to savings exclusively in their local currency,
a theme we've discussed often on this podcast.
And this at a time when Stablecoin adoption was in its relative infancy
and future use cases were somewhat unclear.
Stables has found an audience and more.
In the process of growing a retail user base,
users also started to ask Stables if they could help them with their business needs.
Today, Stables continues to grow and services retail users and businesses alike
when it comes to saving and spending in Stablecoins
with an everlasting focus on the Asia-Pacific region
and meaningful penetration in those markets today.
I think quite highly of Bernardo and the business that he and the team have built.
But beyond that, I was keen to have him join us
as I believe that while we hear a lot about Stablecoin adoption across the globe,
it is insightful to hear these direct accounts from relevant industry leaders,
particularly when it comes to regional activity that we may not see up close as often, if at all.
Without further ado, I hope you enjoy my conversation with Bernardo.
The federal government loans American international group AIG 85 billion dollars.
This is a different kind of market and the Fed is asleep.
The federal government is stepping in to stabilize Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac,
the two mortgage giants that have been threatened by the housing crisis.
The Bank of England has pumped 75 billion pounds more into Britain's ailing economy
with a new round of quantitative easing.
You print a couple trillion dollars and all of a sudden people start to worry.
So out of this worry, we have something called the Bitcoin.
Bitcoin.
Bernie, thanks for coming on.
Who uses Stables?
Who does it serve today?
Who's your audience?
Stables really serves, I'd say, predominantly two different types of user demographic.
Firstly, individuals.
You can think of them as crypto native.
So like people that already have stable coins,
they understand the benefit of all these stable coins and using them on chain.
And they want to kind of utilize them into the real world and crypto agnostic.
So people that they have come about stable coins out of necessity
rather than by being constantly chronically online.
And also we service in businesses.
So on the business vertical, it's almost something that we stumble on by mistake.
We originally started as a consumer product.
And I think it's actually bullish when you see people kind of misusing
your product in a way that you were like,
hey, I don't fully understand what's going on there.
So you go and talk to these people and it turns out they were, you know, businesses.
Yeah, it's unexpected product market fit.
Right.
People or individuals and businesses, they go through unnecessary pain to go and solve a problem.
We go and talk to these folks and they're like, hey, we actually have business
and we're utilizing the platform for these use cases.
And what it really transpires there, it's almost like there is a
platform arbitration rather than regulatory and compliance arbitration,
which basically means that these people realize the stable coins are way better to go and run
their business operation on transaction.
And they just need a platform that allows them to go from stable coin into local currency
in one floor rather than go and stitch it up all together across different five,
six different providers.
Those are the say like I level at the two demographics going forward.
One that I'm quite excited about is the developer demographic.
We started with individual then started service in businesses.
The other thing that we kind of stumbled across coming like, you know, by mistake again,
it's people that want to have access to our rails, you know, one single easy integration.
And these people are either developer businesses, almost like foundation that they really want
access to stable coins in a way that fits their use cases and purposes.
Where are these consumers and businesses?
Where are they in the world?
And what do they do generally?
While we build stable to be like a very global product, inherently we have these
believe stable coins are a global product.
And so you need to be able to service the global audience through the common
discover you by mistake.
However, our vertical and kind of very expertise is really around Asia and MENA.
That's where we see the majority of our flaws originating from and going into.
And as well, like, you know, majority of signups.
And I would say strategically also those jurisdiction, at least to me, are way
more interesting than, you know, other jurisdiction that like kind of far away
and detached from us in a wheelbase across Australia and the broader Asia region.
I think it's like there's a big opportunity there for stable coin to kind of go and
create some connectivity tissue in our otherwise very fragmented market.
There's a lot of different currency, a lot of different use cases and almost countering
quite a large geographical area.
However, there's a lot of trade remittances and money movement across all of these
geographies.
And what you're noticing is like there's a lot of usually like
intermediary banking to go from one place to another, even though somewhat closely
located.
Then it takes a lot of time and effort to get money from point A to point B.
We really believe that like, you know, almost why stable coin have really took
its escape velocity in Africa, Latin, Kuala Lumpur, developed world.
There is a big use cases in, you know, going sort of like fragmented and large markets
such as Asia.
A relatively spread out user base, it sounds like in certain pockets of Asia.
How are users finding you?
And what's the scope of how many people you have on the platform and how much
money moves today?
That is actually like one of the questions that I always tried to answer myself
because we never done any marketing or incentives for the meta.
Today, like it's just through organic discovery and kind of word of mouth.
I think it's like it does help when you do have a beautiful product to get
discovered away.
People are way more prone to go and say, hey, you should go and try the product
is sick.
For instance, I think the other day, somebody from the, I think the Austin
Federer from Cax Solana Foundation was talking about like somebody needs to go
and build a product that allows people to go and issue local bins and they're
like, a gazillion people are just tagging us.
It sounded like we were there actively.
And so I think that's like, it's almost like, you know, when you have a good
product that actually go and solve a pain point for a specific demographic, then
that's how you get these, call it like growth loop of people.
Just like go and say, you should go and try this product is sick and works.
In terms of how much money we're moving, it's been about say 15 months that we
are in market showing numbers.
Today we process about $300 million in TPD through our rails.
That's annualized?
That is over 15 months.
Like now we averaging as say monthly about 12 to 25 mil.
I'm expecting to an exit over the next three to six months as we, you know,
building more specific features, like some of our customers that want to come
on board and, you know, move larger volume are requesting us.
And so it's like, really, I think like the philosophy of building products,
at least for us, we do believe we're a product led growth company is we build
something that we believe we're solving a problem.
Like we of course talk to customer and talk to people and understand what sort
of problem he was solving.
And then by doing that, you know, as I mentioned incidentally, we're solving
other problems for other people in demographics.
Now we're just talking to this new demographic that we're going to found
into a better understanding.
Hey, what do we need to do in order for you to go and move all your volume
over to us?
I think like once you go and craft that that's where things is going to get
very, very interesting because like the volume are considerably higher.
I like how you describe it as growth loops because you have this effect that
we've seen in stable coins, at least where you have stakeholders in the
tether network.
They want to grow tether, which in turn help stables grow.
You have people who are growing Binance, which in turn might lead users to then
find out about stable.
So you have these parallel growth narratives.
I wanted to ask on a couple of points you mentioned, what's a typical
transaction size and what is a typical transaction in so far as are people
sending money to each other in Venmo style?
Are they paying for things or what is a typical transaction behaviorally as
well?
So we say was most of the three types of transaction that we can do it.
At least the way that we talk about it is you can top up your account.
That could be in a stable current transaction or it could be like a
purchase of you depositing local currency through virtual bank accounts or a bank
card to purchase stable coins.
It could be a send transaction.
So it's almost like going from the platform out and this could be in stable
coins or local currencies.
And then it could be a spending transaction.
So we had stable coin card that connects to a stable coin balance.
So on the top up or purchase transaction average or the size that we're seeing at
the moment, it's about two point K.
So relatively large.
Yeah, it's quite large.
It gets queued up because there'll be people that do like big transaction and
people do very small transactions.
So it kind of ends up there in the middle.
On the send, it's about kind of similar.
I'd say like a little higher, like three point four K.
And that's usually what you see is like most of the time it's people sending to
local currencies.
And then on the card size, we're seeing about $70 per transaction average or
the size.
What's interesting there is we do see increasingly the amount of spending
being completed on everyday purchases.
So that at least like to me is an indication of people utilizing stables
more and more for their everyday and becoming their everyday digital US dollar
account, which I think is like it could unlock a bunch of very interesting stuff
down the road.
But it's all like, you know, very encouraging, especially on the frequency
of our offer this transaction, like all of these customers that transact, usually
they are repeat transactor.
And the interesting insights is that once you manage to give somebody a card,
they becoming a much better user than a user that doesn't have a card.
I remember seeing that also back in the fintech days, once you manage to get a
person to utilize their phone and give them a card, their LTV grows
exponentially effectively.
They can use it daily at that point.
They don't need to rely on joint financial products.
Right.
How do total deposits compare to volume?
Do people keep a lot of money on the platform as well that they're not
immediately using for payments?
Not really, because at the moment the platform is really optimized for
velocity of money rather than like kind of money sync.
And it's also like no reason for them to hold the balance with us other than
spend it or on-ramp it and off-ramp it.
Just because like at the moment there's no yield component or any sort of
incentives for you to hold the balance there, which is a great opportunity there
to go and do something about it.
I think it's like you can go and start gamifying it even further.
Like wouldn't it be cool if you have a magic balance that goes up in real time
that you can spend, buy stuff from, or remit from, which is like that big
kind of UX unlock that I think only programmable money really allows you
to go and do.
And it actually happens rather than like, you know, numbering a database
kind of thinking out.
So I think there's like a lot of stuff there that like it's yet to play out
and, you know, big opportunity on optimizing then almost like for deposit
size versus velocity of money.
It's interesting that, especially given the parts of the world that you guys
serve, that this more of a spending friendly product already has that level
of traction.
Because I would imagine if anything, the main demand would be to store money
and maybe earn yield in dollars as opposed to for the spend aspect.
If I was to listen to my customer, I would already have yield out.
It's one of those like more requested feature.
We did explore it for a while.
That's how we actually originally started.
But at the time, I think like now there's a lot more regulatory clarity there.
Given like until more recently, it was seen as a very risky and kind of gray
area to go and offer yield on customers' deposit.
Like you see other people that just say earn reward.
Like there's like other structure that you could go and do it without
passing through yield.
But yeah, definitely that's one of the things that customer wants.
They want to have the ability to just like store stable coins, see number
goes up, spend from that balance without having to go to different platform.
That being said, I think it's like this is just an indication almost like how
stable coins are in fact a superior form of money for payments more broadly.
These people come to us because they either got the financial system kind of failed them,
they don't serve because they consider it to be either high-risk clients or it's hard for them to
go and stitch all these different payment methods together.
While I do want to do yield, I also think payment itself is like big enough for the vertical
to just go and be the whole business owner.
It's telling also the transaction size, like you mentioned, that these are
a couple thousand dollar transactions right now.
It's clear that for meaningful movements of money, people are preferring this system.
If someone makes a card payment using stables, how does it settle?
Presumably, that'll be to merchants in a variety of countries, right?
Yes. The way that it works is we do this process called just-in-time funding.
Effectively, the difference is from at least the traditional concept of having a card balance.
Back in the day, you have a card, you got to move money onto the card,
the card becomes a value store card, and then you got to spend all the money on the card.
Usually, it wasn't possible to go and take them out.
The only way was to spend it all.
It's like Starbucks.
Right. Yeah. While it's functional, it's not ideal.
Also because I think back in the days, there were a lot of these crypto cards
that they were using this model and then they disappear overnight.
It happened to me once.
Yours went away?
No, they don't run away.
Well, pretty much because they're basically doing things they're not supposed to.
Back in the day, card issuers weren't as friendly towards crypto more broadly.
These people were actually saying, we're doing something completely different.
And then once they get caught by the scheme, they get cut off.
But what happened is you have the money on the card, the money's gone.
And so ideally, the way that these things work is really do things properly
so that that doesn't happen to your customer, number one.
Number two is just-in-time funding cards.
You don't actually need to store user balances on a card.
You can just use the delegated wealth model to basically go and say,
when you go to a store and you tap at a post, what's happening is there's a thing
that goes from the post to our backend to check, hey, do you have enough money
for this transaction size?
If you do, return to Android, return, clear the transaction.
And then at the end of the day, when the merchant goes and captures the transaction,
we would do all the on-chain settlements.
So you say it's a $5 transaction for a coffee.
The merchant at the end of the day goes and captures the transaction.
This $5 on-chain then moves to a float account, a settlement account.
And then from the settlement account, we are framping.
We do the settlement with the merchants directly.
And that happens on a number of currency, of course.
People travel and do a bunch of stuff in the day-to-day life with the scheme.
We just need to settle with the scheme.
Usually that's how it works.
So the card issuer, we just send the money into a local currency
and then they take care of the merchant.
Yeah, it seems like an attractive product,
especially if you're a digital nomad type remote worker
and you just want to have an account denominated in dollars
where you can use in any country or place that you go to.
A hundred percent.
I mean, I don't know if you ever had the pleasure
of try opening up a brokerage account, like when you would try and get T-bills
or access to the dollar.
For some people, it's actually not that hard.
But then giving certain jurisdiction is actually quite impossible.
It's either like capital control that don't allow you to do it
or the amount of documentation that you require
just to like even buy one single dollar is staggering.
These onboarding forms, they're just coming straight out of the settlement.
It takes you like six hours to complete it.
And maybe you get it done in a month's time you onboarded
versus just streamlining completely in a mobile first experience
that you just go, let's go see you.
Let's make sure that we have enough details
about who's actually initiating these transactions.
We make access to dollar simple and easy and fast.
You should be able to go and buy your first dollar, spend your dollar
or send money in three minutes type of things.
Those are the benchmark rather than go and say,
yeah, we'll get back to you in six weeks.
It's a big unlock when it comes to almost like the zero to one moment.
What stablecoin really unlock is that magic moment of,
hold on a second, I can go and access dollar in under three minutes
versus legacy system that either prevent me completely from accessing this dollar
or they're just like putting all this red tape around me
being able to access this dollar.
And so like, you know, making everything slower and more cumbersome.
We've talked a lot about your offering.
Why did you guys choose to call it stables?
I think you hear maybe the word dollar or send a lot
in names of companies operating in this space.
Why did you go after the namesake stables?
It's actually a bit of a funny story.
Stables is a rebrand from our originally previous name that we had.
It's called TIK, T-triple-I-K.
At the time at stablecoins, we're in that hall in general.
And we were like, hey, because really the way that we see
is there is a problem to be solved for us for crypto native
that such as ourselves, they add digital dollar,
but it's actually hard to go and use this digital dollar in the real world.
And then there is the next iteration of the product is like
go and get the normies to utilize all these special rails,
magic internet money rails.
And so stables is really, it's the jargon for stablecoins in their industry.
But it's also like, I think there's a funny comparison
that is also a place where the horses stay.
And so like the way they were thinking about it was
we're going to have a stables of product.
We thought it was funny.
Yeah, it's a stable for stables.
Right. But it's a great asset because now stablecoins are hot
and we are stables money.
It's our own trademark.
Maybe that's valuable on his own, I suppose.
That's probably a valuable domain too, I figure.
Right. Yeah.
And at the time it wasn't very hot.
We got a good deal on it.
Let's put it that way.
When people talk about your guys' platform,
do they describe it as a neobank or a savings product?
Because a stablecoin account isn't something that I imagine.
Like you said, you have this viral effect.
I wouldn't think people are describing it that way.
I have a mixed feeling at times about the word neobank
because you should be calling things for what they are.
But we're definitely not a bank.
But that is also the things that people resonate the most.
It's like, oh, it's a neobank.
I can buy things.
I can store things.
I can spend from it.
Familiar with Revolut or DeWise, that's how they probably like to categorize it at.
But the thing is more about payments.
The way that people talk about Sable is more like a payment platform.
You can load it up with stablecoins and you can give your stablecoins real utility.
I think it's probably going to become a quasi-neobank
once you're able to go and offer more of an earned saving offering.
Because then you have payments.
You have money sink.
You have broad opportunities.
But yeah, I think it's at the moment it's more on the payment angle side of things.
On an offering, I think that's how people really,
especially in this industry, that's how people see it.
As much as we believe stablecoins are new,
I think there's actually way more understood that,
especially I think in the deeper South, way more understood than us in the West.
Just because we don't need to use them necessarily.
And people do understand the stablecoins are for payments.
And people understand what a stablecoin is and what are the benefits of the stablecoins.
And so once you have a stablecoin, you can do one or two things.
You either hold it or you own an offering.
So I think that's the easiest way to think about it.
You go from magic internal money to real-world money and do stuff with it.
At the moment, that's how it is in my change.
How do banks behave towards you guys?
Do they want to work with you?
Do they not like you?
What's their sentiment?
It's been four years that we've been swimming against the current, I would say.
I think this is evolving, especially now with the progress and changes in administrations
and almost perspective towards what stablecoins are going to enable.
It was really hard.
It's still very hard.
One of the things that are actually very hard in this space,
which is basically I think the only thing that's actually worthwhile doing, by the way,
everything else will eventually get commoditized.
If it hasn't been already commoditized,
getting the banking rail and working with the bank is one of the two things.
If you do things properly, if you have proper compliance framework,
KYC, AMF, call it global program, then now banks are way more open and receptive to go and work.
With stablecoin providers, to give you an example, four years ago,
we started working on one of the largest payment processors in Southeast Asia.
We started as a pilot in only one country, in the Philippines.
And it took us four years to get to the point that now they want to go and open up all of the rail to
us, which is going to be highly significant.
It takes time.
And it takes a lot of work to get where you're at because they need to get comfortable with you.
They need to see that you have the right processes and framework in place.
They need to see that you last the test of time.
They actually run a real business.
They're handling compliance and all of those processes appropriately.
And then you have the right people to go and operate the licenses.
And usually they just want to work with licensed businesses, which we are in a number of
jurisdictions.
And so that gives you, I think, now a structural advantage versus just like go and utilize
somebody else's infrastructure.
The way I see it, it's either going to be almost like you have a million customers and you can
distribute to this customer very quickly.
I think user experience plays a big role in that.
Or you actually own the licenses and the infrastructure that you can allow and enable
other people to go and build experiences on it.
I think something that has always been very misunderstood about Stables is that we do both.
While we play at the app layer, we also have all the licenses to go and do all the
info play that we want to.
Right.
And so now, because we've been in market for so long, because we got traction, now this
conversation is becoming a whole lot more streamlined, interesting, and almost fruitful.
Because now these people that come and talk to us, because they want to get their footer
into stable coins, they want to get stable coins flowing to the platform.
A company that probably back in the days, even like a couple of years ago, didn't fully
understand the space.
Now they understand that not playing in the space is going to...
There's an opportunity to go there.
And so they just want to go and play with people that they're licensed, they've done
it for a while, and they're the right people on the team to go and serve those types of
laws and use cases, of course.
It's never easy.
They're late to the game, but you start to realize the cost of not participating is higher
than the cost they had perceived of participating before.
You touched on compliance.
The primary criticism that I hear for an app like this, let's say, is a user onboards funds,
they convert to stable coins, they send it to a wallet.
How do you know that wallet isn't in North Korea or that transaction is illicit or used
for money laundering?
What's your response?
And how do you guys look at compliance and avoiding potential illicit activity on the
platform?
Maybe the good preamble here is the other non-consensus things that we've done
back in the day.
And aside from getting excited about stable coins when nobody was excited about stable
coins, it was like, hey, these stable coins are going to become the future of money.
And they're actually better for money the way that we understand it.
However, because it's money nonetheless, you need to approach it like a fully
already regulated financial product.
And at the time it was kind of on the outskirt of it's still unsure what this is.
And we always approach it like a fully regulated financial product.
So we got financial licenses to go and structure a regulated financial product.
We literally structure a fully regulated and compliant remittance product powered by
stable coins.
Some of these products, they structure across Australia, Europe, Canada, and soon UAE.
And in some of these countries, such as Australia, the regulator pride themselves to
be one of the toughest regulator in the world when it comes to financial services.
And so for us, the fact that we've been able to kind of structure product that clears
Australia's standards basically means that we can then go and scale this globally.
Because the Commonwealth is like, while not the same everywhere, it's like quite
shared across the major economies.
So if you can go and cover it there, then you can go and export it elsewhere, which
is like what happened with us.
In terms of how do we approach risk and compliance and more broadly like customer
onboarding, when you come to the platform, you can decide to sign up as individual as
a business.
We can see you or can be you.
And that basically means self fees, proof of address, you'll be all directors,
shareholders, whatever you name it.
So once you have an account, I mean, it just doesn't stop there.
Compliance, it's one of those things that like, you know, as a founder, you go and say
it's painful because it costs a lot of money.
But then it's really one of the few assets, you know, going back to licensing, that you
really have a hand.
And if you do it properly, that's what makes the business valuable.
Because you can go and grow very quickly by kind of turning a blind eye to compliance.
But then that actually devalues your business a lot, especially as we become more and more
institutionalized.
People value the fact that you're running things properly without compromising there.
The things that we do is, you know, we build our own proprietary fraud and risk engine,
where we're feeding a bunch of data that we have on our customers to making sure of
we have identified certain risky patterns that, you know, we know they usually led to
fraud.
And so that would kind of flag certain activities.
We're also using like, you know, transaction monitoring tool.
We're also using KYT tools to the point that like, you know, we know that you don't
send money to a North Korean wallet.
These things, by the way, it's a never-ending battle.
Every time that we usually launch a new product, the way that it works is like you have all
this control, you launch a new product.
And then what happens is you realize there was an area that you were exposed, somebody
comes and kind of exploit it.
And then you go and say, cool, now I got the data to go and make my system stronger.
Over time, that's how you build battle-tested systems, because, you know,
similar in FinTech is the same.
Fraudsters, very smart.
Getting better.
They're always changing the system.
They always adapt into the new meta and the new tooling.
And so you always need to be up to scratch with that.
Otherwise, they're always going to find a way to go and exploit loopholes, platforms,
and whatever.
Right now, the way that we see working is KYC, Transaction Monitoring, KYT, and then
our own proprietary fraud and risk engine, where all the data effectively gets fed into.
And then there's almost a decision engine there.
Based on all of these data points, then we're able to go and make decisions in real time.
This is a piece of the puzzle that people talk about publicly a lot.
But for you guys internally, what are the risks or the single risk that you keep in
mind mostly as being paramount to the business and that you do most of your work to try and
mitigate or avoid?
First of all, it would be we need to make sure that we know what our customers are.
Our biggest risk, single-handedly, is KML and KYC.
And again, while it adds to your business value if you do it properly, it's highly deterrent
if you don't do it properly, right?
If you let bad actors through your platform, then that's how the business goes to zero.
You get fined, you literally go and destroy all the things that you built from the data.
So I think for us, that is the main risk and concerns.
It's like making sure that we are abiding to KML and KYC.
Rules and laws, we have a full-time chief risk officer and general counsel on the team
that usually you don't get to see many early days startups.
But that's because we understand we're dealing with people's money.
And so it becomes paramount to make sure that you don't screw it up there.
The other thing is security, more broadly.
We want to make sure that we have all the right control to prevent account takeover,
to prevent loss of funds, and whatnot.
So we have implemented to a phase device that the intelligence, there is biometrics,
there's a bunch of smarts that when you're using the product, you might not necessarily
appreciate that it takes a long time to go and build.
But those are the things that are actually important when you go and build consumer
purchasing products.
Because if your customer comes and uses the app and then somehow somebody is able to come
and enter into the account and drain your funds, then it's never good.
It's almost like those two things, at least at KML at night.
Making sure that the money is where it's supposed to be and making sure that nobody
that is not supposed to go and touch the money, touches it.
I think good pieces to keep in mind for anyone building a product in this general areas.
I'm sure we'll see many of them.
Yeah, don't screw that up.
Bernie, thank you for joining.
I really enjoyed the conversation and I'm sure we'll chat again soon.
Sounds like a plan.
It was a pleasure being here.
Go Stables.
Yeah, thanks, Ben.
See you later.
Thanks for listening to another episode of On the Brink with Castle Island.
To find out more about Castle Island, visit castleisland.vc.
To listen to all of our podcast episodes, please go to onthebrink-podcast.com
or just click on the tab in our website.
Thanks for listening.